Guide to the Warren Hiram Lowenhaupt Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Warren Hiram Lowenhaupt papers
1891-1967
1910-1967
MS 884
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(5 boxes, 1 folio)
The papers consist of correspondence, photographs, writings, printed matter, financial records, and memorabilia documenting Warren Lowenhaupt's years as a student at Yale University (1910-1917), at Columbia Law School (1926), as an officer in World War I, and as curator and research associate at the Yale University Library (1952-1967). His principal correspondents are Emile Victor Bonnet, Charles Burpee, John Lindsay Moore, Frederick B. Kaye, William Lyon Phelps and Arthur E. Case. Much of the correspondence and financial papers relate to purchases of rare books, bookplates, and art objects. Approximately two hundred photographs are also in the papers, nearly half of which show European scenes and events relating to World War I.
Lowenhaupt, Warren Hiram, 1891-1967
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry S. and Malcolm D. Lowenhaupt, 1970.
Scope and Contents
The Warren Hiram Lowenhaupt Papers contain correspondence, photographs, writings, printed matter, and other papers pertaining to Lowenhaupt's career as a student at Yale University (Class of 1914) and Columbia Law School, an officer in World War I, secretary to Justice Tounley of the Appellate Division of the Supreme Court of New York, and collector and Curator of Bookplates at Yale University.
The correspondence is divided into general, arranged chronologically, and select, which contains substantial runs of letters from four individuals and from Yale University. Lowenhaupt's correspondents include friends, family members, and professional associates; among them are Charles Burpee, John Lindsay Moore, W. Lyon Phelps, and Lowenhaupt's classmate Arthur E. Case. Topics discussed include Lowenhaupt's career, literature, and the collecting of rare books and incunabula. There are also letters from friends serving in World War I, and letters discussing American attitudes towards France and England during and after the war. The Yale University correspondence deals mainly with Lowenhaupt's gifts to the university of rare books and book plates. Correspondence relating directly to Lowenhaupt's military service is interfiled with other military papers such as orders, passes, and so forth (folders 48-57), while correspondence concerning his legal practice is interfiled with other papers arranged by case (folders 58-83).
The remaining papers in this collection are several short writings by Lowenhaupt, including his master's thesis, "Life and Works of Archibald Pitcairne, M.D.," accompanied by copies of Pitcairne's correspondence; personal financial papers such as check books, bank statements, and stock reports; further financial papers, largely bills and receipts, pertaining to purchases of rare books, book plates, and art objects; printed matter, including various writings on literature and book collecting, maps, and catalogues; memorabilia from Yale University and Columbia Law School, and other periods of Lowenhaupt's life; concert programs, one autographed by Nellie Melba; and almost two hundred photographs of Lowenhaupt, friends and family, and Europe during and after World War I.
These papers were given to Yale University by Henry S. and Malcolm D. Lowenhaupt in 1970. Related correspondence can be found in the Frederick B. Kaye [formerly Kugelman] Papers in the Humanities and Fine Arts Manuscript Group (No. 590), and in the Records of the Yale Librarian (YRG 32).
Biographical / Historical
WARREN HIRAM LOWENHAUPT was born in Brooklyn; N. Y., August 13, 1891, and has lived in Plainfield, N. J., Hartford, Conn., and Middle Haddam, Conn.
His father, John P. Lowenhaupt, was born in Bavaria, in 1855, but has spent most of his life in New York City. He is a fruit grower. Mrs. Lowenhaupt was Marie E. Karbaum; she lived in New York City before marriage, and died March 7, 1909, in Hartford. There were four sons in the family; three now living.
Warren prepared for Yale at the Hartford Public High School. He received a High Oration, was the Ten Eyck Orator, and was the recipient of the Berkeley premium in Latin composition. He received honorable mention in the Andrew D. White history prize competition, tied for first place in the Donald Annis English and German competition prize, won the John Addison Porter prize in American history, received honorable mention in the John Addison Porter University prize competition (1913), and held a Scott Hurtt scholarship. He was a member of the Freshman Class and Intercollegiate Debating teams, an alternate on the Interdepartment Team, and a member of the Yale Debating Association, Pundits and the Society for the Study of Socialism..
He received his B.A. degree from Yale in 1914, his M.A. in 1916, and his Ph.D. in 1917. In 1926 he received a LL.B. from Columbia. Lowenhaupt was an assistant in English at Yale from 1915-1917. He served as an officer in World War I, and was secretary to Justice Tounley of the Appellate Division of the Supreme Court of New York. Lowenhaupt was curator of bookplates and research associate at the Yale University Library, 1952-1960, and an honorary trustee, 1961-1967.
He died October 4, 1967.
Book collecting; Law; Libraries; World War, 1914-1918; Bookplates; Lawyers; Bonnet, Emile Victor; Burpee, Charles W. (Charles Winslow), 1859-; Case, Arthur Ellicott, 1894-1946; Lowenhaupt, Warren Hiram, 1891-1967; Moore, John Lindsay; Pearson, J. Sidney; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943; Ward, Renee Fairfax; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1914; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Library
- Inventory, 1891-(1910-1967); 2 linear feet (5 boxes, 1 folio)
  - General correspondence, 1910-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-13)
  - Select correspondence
    - Bonnet, Emile Victor, 1938-1952 (Box 1, Folder 14-24)
      - Passport, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Kaye [formerly Kugelman], Frederick B., 1916-1919 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    - Kaye [formerly Kugelman], Frederick B., 1920-1924, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 26a-27)
    - Pearson, J. Sidney, 1950-1954 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Ward, Renee Fairfax, 1947-1967 (Box 2, Folder 29-31)
    - Yale University, 1921-1964 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Writings
    - Freshman theme, "Milton and the Pamela Prayer,", [ca. 1910-1911] (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Senior theme, "Impeachment in the National Government,", [ca. 1913-1914] (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - "A Pre-Beethovenite Movement," Yale Literary Magazine, pp. 240-44, 1914 March (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "Cromwell Debates,", 1914 March 11 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Theater reviews, 1915, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - M.A. thesis, "Life and Works of Archibald Pitcairne, M.D."
      - Typescript, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Copies of Pitcairne's letters, [ca. 1916] (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Interview with Capt. Arthur E. Case, 1920 January 7 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Letter to the editor of the London Mercury, 1920 November 6 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "The Writing of Milton's Eikonoklastes ," Studies in Philology, pp. 29-51; with notes and printed matter, 1923 January (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "The Evolution of the Corporate Mortgage,", undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - "Meditations on a Theme of Shakespeare,", undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Manuscript essays, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - "Bibliographie sur Douris,", undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Footnotes for unidentified book, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Military papers, 1917-1922, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 48-57)
    General note
    See also: Folio
  - Legal files
    - Barbieri v. Moore, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Bowman v. Craig, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Cagney, David E., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Empire City Savings Bank v. Plymgar Realty Co., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Kohan, Joseph H., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Old Charter Financial Corp. v. Bauer et al., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Rail Estates, Inc., v. City Farmers Trust Co., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Dodge, Kathleen C., Trust, 1930, 1939-1959, n.d (Box 3, Folder 65-66)
    - Bruning v. Bruning, 1930-1931 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Iselin v. Livermore, 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Manila Import Co. v. International Reptile Tanning Co., 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - People v. Zalo Credit Corp., 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Smith Trust, 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Hammond v. Cherry, 1930-1932 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Bouillon v. Raven, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Chase v. Krech, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Guaranty Trust Co. as trustee under will of Albert A. C. Asher, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Emigrant Industrial Savings Bank v. Rose Merkt, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Ledyard v. Thebaud, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - New York Title and Mortgage Co. v. Finlin Building Corp. et al., 1931 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Steinbock v. Seligman, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Lang v. Bonnet, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Jutte, William B., 1945, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Jacobson mortgage, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - DeSairigne v. Gould, 1952, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Financial papers
    - Personal, 1921-1957, undated (Box 4, Folder 84-86)
    - Financial and other papers concerning rare books and art objects, 1928-1957, undated (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Printed matter
    - Writings by others, 1924-1937, undated (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - Maps, catalogues, etc., 1932-1936, undated (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Memorabilia
    - Birth certificate, voting record, etc., 1891-1926 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Yale University: programs, certificates, printed matter, 1912-1943 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Columbia Law School: programs, certificates, grade reports, 1925-1926 (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Concert programs, lists of recordings, related papers, 1926-1937, undated (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Newspaper clippings, addresses, miscellaneous notes, etc., 1926-1941, undated (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Photographs
    - W. H. Lowenhaupt (10 photogrpahs), 1914-1936 (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Emile Bonnet (12 photographs), 1937-1938, undated (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Other individuals, mostly unidentified (92 photographs), 1916-1937, undated (Box 5, Folder 97)
      General
    - World War I (23 photographs), [ca. 1914-1922] (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - European scenes (57 photographs), [ca. 1920-1940] (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Negatives, undated (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Military papers: certificates, 1917-1918 (Box 6)
  - 3 photographs, 1947, undated (Box 6)